Of the time and I'm pretty sure it'll happen
over the next two days
That said I'd like to introduce our first speaker George. Do you want to start coming up?
George Hotz
Is a pretty interesting guy
He had his first 15 minutes of fame as I understand it hacking the iPhone as a teenager. Is that right? George?
and
And it's George will correct me if I'm wrong in any of this
And his second 15 minutes of fame when he went into his garage and came out a couple of months later
having hacked his car to be self-driving that set him off on a
project that he's still in the middle of creating an operating system for
Self-driving both retrofitting existing cars and for new cars and and that's what's gonna tell us about today George
Hey
Oh
Okay, I'm good
When I talk I try to be really concrete with words, um, if I say anything that doesn't sound concrete, please ask me a question
Last
couple months ago
I started working with like formal languages like talk and Isabel and everything could be specified
rigidly, and I think a lot of
Definitions for a lot of things are just thrown around and there is no formal definition of them
And then it's a question what you're really saying. A lot of people can have conversations where two people just talk past each other
Because they have different definitions of a word
But you know some disciplines like math have found beautiful ways to solve this by giving things formal
Definitions so if I'm informal about anything, I mean it's obviously an informal talk, but I'm happy to clarify
So when you think of self-driving cars, what's the first company you think of I?
Hear a few Tesla's I also heard way moe
I think I think
yeah way mo is way mo is probably the one that captures the
Perhaps national consciousness of what self-driving cars are or the other one people mention is uber uber?
Actually got the most press about self-driving cars. If you do a Google Trends search for them. It's when uber killed somebody
so
but the traditional
Maybe this is just because a lot of marketing dollars have been poured into it
The traditional idea of self-driving cars is the way Moe. It's a car with no people in it and
You can call it from an app that it will drive down your idyllic suburban
street and it will pull up on the curb next to you and it will flash its little lights and be like way Moe is
Waiting for passengers to get on board
You could see this in the Google ads and it does not reflect the reality of driving
At all if you if you guys have seen a way Moe ad
Yeah, but you know so you pull up oh look everyone's so happy they're riding around in a way Moe
Way Moe is valued at a hundred and seventy five billion dollars despite
Not only not making profit, but I believe never making any revenue
So this this notion of self-driving cars may be distinct from Tesla is known as and we'll get to Tesla
But it's known as level four
Maybe this is the term that the levels don't really mean anything, but that's just the term people use
What it technically means is a car that's capable of full autonomy in restricted areas
so
full autonomy in restricted areas the
Application people immediately think of is ride-sharing
Ride-sharing is only a very small percent of rides people who?
Google's notorious for this if they don't think about what
Life is like for most people most people don't live in the Bay Area
Where they can call an uber and have an uber arrive in three minutes
I'm from suburban, New Jersey very nice area, but you call an uber. I'll be twenty minutes
So ride-sharing is only a very small percent of rides most people still in cars
and
Level four self-driving is a strictly worse product
So if ride-sharing
Can't even capture these markets. How do people expect self-driving cars to be able to
so first and foremost
Anything that's level four. So also level four or says something about usually how it's technically done way
Moe uses High Definition maps a very high precision like precise to the centimeter maps of an area
Uses lidar that can register every object up to three hundred meters away
This is not how humans drive at all
But because of these this HD map requirement they have a smaller service area
They're also slower
So way most travel the speed limit they come to full stops at stop signs and
They slow down at the slightest hint of hesitation
Which may be if you're trying to design your thing to make sure there's never a PR disaster for your company like uber
It's the right call
But if I'm sitting there, oh man, y'know I gotta get downtown or home way. Mo is 18 minutes uber saying 12
I'm gonna take an uber
There also, more expensive
So this might change this will probably change in the future everything eventually gets cheaper
but right now when you look at away, mo those cars cost about
300,000 to 500,000 to retrofit
Again, Google thinks oh, yeah. Well, we pay all our software engineers 200k a year salaries uber drivers ain't makin 200k. Um,
so
They're they're they're they're more expensive
the
Autonomous vehicle vision wouldn't even be a revolution at best
It's cheaper ride-sharing. A lot of times people get caught up in notions because they see
Futuristic looking stuff like this and think that this is going to have some
revolutionary impact
But they don't think about what the exact same product would be with a human
so all those chatbot AI companies criticized like
They're just humans doing the chatting, but they put AI in the name and they're there for some reason their valuation is way higher
It's a scam
So who's profiting off this game
This is a company drive day I
So they use all they're all you read their medium posts aw
They're unbelievable with the well, so we want to make sure that our self-driving car is capable of operating in multiple areas
So we hired engineers all over the world
What does have anything to do with that?
The very very kind of lofty language
Then when you get down to the root of what they actually made they made like a neighborhood shuttle bus
You know those like like like those buses that that ride around retirement homes that look like this
It's not self-driving. There's a human in the driver's seat. They made a
77 million dollar
Retirement home shuttle bus. What even is the global market for retirement home shuttle buses
I don't know
anybody
Consulting with people about the ethics of autonomous vehicles all well
So if I'm driving down the street and and there's a baby in the way
But there's a tree do I swerve and kill the driver to save them has this ever happened to a human?
Has this ever been a real scenario?
Cars are incredibly dangerous and 90% of accidents are caused by drivers who are drunk distracted or asleep
not because they swerve to not hit a baby yet this captures again a
conversation about self-driving cars that's completely disproportional to any
Remote impact it may have but a lot of people are making money off this and they're there branding themselves
It's like well, we're gonna consult with the city of Beverly Hills about their autonomous vehicle strap. What?
This stuff's not a thing. I'm in this one
So in the in the gold rush so you look at the the cruise acquisition
Probably actually a good vote for GM but then it was all the follow-ons to the cruise acquisition
this was the
Delfy spent four hundred fifty million dollars for demo quality software that drives around a block with a human of a driver's seat
This was done by Stanford in in during 2011 and the DARPA urban challenge and even better
They open sourced their code
They paid four hundred fifty thousand forty fifty million dollars probably for a few engineers and some code that's effectively open-source
So what's not a scam we gotta have the the positive atom actually sit here and rant about all the scammers for for an hour
This is car sold in America
Personal vehicle ownership is on the rise and not going anywhere for a long time
Might convert to electric. I think it will
Give it
time for the infrastructure to proliferate but personal vehicle ownership is not going anywhere because
How much cheaper would self-driving cars even be the nuber how much of the cost of the ride-sharing is the human driver?
About half the other half is maintenance of the car and in fleet and fuel and lots of other things
So it would even make goobers that are twice as cheap, but uber tries this we can already do twice as cheap uber today
It's called subsidies and they still, you know, can't get more than a few percent of a lot of these markets
This is US car ownership. This is Chinese car ownership
Huge potential market car ownership will continue for a long time
like we're not going to
Rethink and revolutionize the way that we have cars people like owning cars for the same reason people like owning houses
So if people are going to continue to buy cars, what does a better car look like?
You think of cell phones
You go back people had cell phones in the early 2000s, but no one really had smart phones
So what does there's a benefit Kevin's quote, right? What does a smart phone on wheels look like question down front on your right?
Would would this change if it was
Mixed use in the sense of if you want to get on an interstate. It will only be with the driverless car
So you flip a switch or something and then when you get off it goes back to human driving. Well, so
Yeah, I mean you can build that. We're already seeing systems like that today with test auto pilot
We're seeing systems where they still require monitoring
But they can do a lot of the work on the interstate and I do think this is the direction that we are headed
When it comes to we're going to rezone interstates as autonomous vehicle only zones. That's I mean
Some legislature person can might talk about that kind of stuff. But in reality, there's no reason to do it
Yeah, maybe you have you know, this is the autonomous Lane kind of like the HOV Lane, okay, I could see that happening
But does that answer your question?
So
On a lot of new cars today in fact, it's becoming standard on a lot of manufacturers you're starting to see driver assistance technology
So don't view
Autonomous vehicles as a binary like there's either you know
A human driver or there's no human driver all of those way Mo's driving around Chandler Arizona still have a human in the driver seat
That still has to be there to
intervene in case the car makes any mistakes
So instead of thinking about it like a cliff think about it as a gradual as a gradual increase to full autonomy
So we had cruise control cruise control came out in the first cars before in 70s. It's automatic gas
So when you're on the highway instead of having to keep your foot of gas pedal you press the button and the car will will
Handle the gas for you not so great if there's another car in a way
Because it will slam right into that car if you set the cruise control at 65, so that's why we have adaptive cruise control
How many people have cars with adaptive cruise control?
Cool a lot of you
It's common in mice
So it's the car will the car will do the brake for you and will keep you a safe following distance from the car in
front of you and then
lane centering
as distinct from Lane Keeping Assist
Which will correct you if you're drifting out of the lane Lane centering
Actively keeps you in the land how many people have a car with Lane Center?
Okay less. So if you guys didn't see the hands it's about 50% you with adaptive cruise control about 20% with Lane centering
All of these combined gas brake and steering that's all of driving a
Lot of
Manufacturers were selling their cruise control systems and their dapping cruise control systems in the lane keeping system
All kind of on separate pages if you've ever tried to navigate
The OEMs website. I think Tesla did a great job with the branding on this when they came out to test the autopilot
Tesla autopilot is just these same features but packaged into one
Nice Oh
Test autopilot. Okay, cool. What is autopilot? Oh, it drives the car for you. Well, that's not really what Auto powered on the plane does
But interesting interesting pyaare around it, they know how to be provocative. So, this is a Paul Graham tweet
The Tesla Model S was like the iPhone
And that all the manufacturers now have to copy it. The difference is many don't realize it yet
So when these things come out
Even blackberry is scared. There's there's initial articles about all the iPhone will never take off because people want a physical keyboard
Blackberry doesn't think this blackberry starts working or if you guys remember the blackberry storm
they tried they tried to they tried to stay around but
they didn't I
Spoke with someone
I believe it was from from Mitsubishi and they said there's no way that we can now build electric cars
Because because Tesla is Tesla is so far had on the battery technology. They have a 5-2 lead in the battery technology
There's no supplier. You can go to to buy Tesla's battery from
but even if you built a car with the same range and specs as a Tesla
nobody would buy it because they're also five years ahead in a
Huge number of other areas like the operating system like the supercharger network
So, I don't know what's gonna happen with it with what the car industry but
This is kind of where we come in I was approached by a friend
To build a new to build the vision system for Tesla autopilot before it launched
Tesla was using a mobile eye chip. So mobile eye is a
really the original a task company and I've come to respect them a lot more throughout this journey because they've been saying a lot of
His self-driving cars a scam stuff for a long time
And they are they were acquired for fifteen billion dollars by Intel
Not a bad price. Sorry Intel Botham name an Intel acquisition that's gone on to be a successful company
You get bought by Facebook. You're successful you get bought by Intel you're dead
Uh-huh
Thanks for everything though whatsapp Instagram oculus
Let's go sold a million of those things
so
I'm working I met with Elon a few times who talked about
a deal for building the vision system
But eventually the deal kind of fell through I'll chalk it up to a miscommunication
And I come up with this idea for a company. Okay build better test the autopilot
sell to automakers be rich
Just pitch that I get this is the pitch that I gave to VCS and it sounds like a good pitch. I
talked about the smartphone stuff and I'm like look, I mean Tesla's running iOS
We're gonna build the Android
So we did we did step one. It's called open pilot
Um open pilot. I have a little explainer video made by one of our
Community members after this but it's effectively
autopilot
for cars people actually have
So this is this is a little what is open pilot open pilot is an advanced driver assistance
System that turns your car's lane keep assist function from this
To this as well as provides smoother and safer radar adaptive cruise control
Open pilot allows you to be driving hands-free and feet free for long periods of time without intervention even more so on interstates and highways
Everything is controlled by open pilot, but it's easy to intervene at any time. But how does this all work?
You need three pieces of hardware all bought from coma ai slash shop
first the giraffe
This device converts your car's lane keep assist camera connector into a more Universal port for the next piece of hardware
Which is the gray panda the Panda receives information from your car and can also send information as well
This is what sends the car commands such as speed up slow down and turn the wheel in either direction
It also has a high-precision GPS antenna used to create HD maps as you drive
Finally the e on this is the main device that drives your car first plugged into the Panda then mounted on your windshield
it sees your car's existing radar information which shows exactly how far away the car in front of you is
With this it instructs the car to speed up and slow down as needed
it also has a high quality camera that looks for lane lines in the road and tells the wheel to stay exactly centered in the
lane lines at all times
As an added bonus. It is also a fantastic dashcam with free unlimited cloud storage
Open pilot runs on Honda's Toyota's
Acuras Lexus GM in Hyundais with even more car support being worked on every day and the best part
Altogether this setup costs less than
$1,000 check if your existing car is compatible then go buy a neon panda enter after day and upgrade your car to the future
That's our slogan
So
Back to the the the the the business plan build better Tesla autopilot. Well, I really think you're not really gonna build better test autopilot
because
Tesla autopilot is
Not a fixed target
It's much better right now than Tesla autopilot when it came out
Is it better than Tesla autopilot now? No
Because Tesla's good engineers
when I saw what Tesla was doing with autopilot like
When I compared myself to the way that like Toyota and auto manufacturers and even the tier ones Delphian Bosch are thinking about this
They're thinking in old ways. They're coding in. Well, we have to code everything in Misra C and run it on
32-bit
freescale trike or micro processors that have as 'old these safety ratings and
This doesn't really make sense
You're not gonna get
Functional safety, you're not gonna be able to get a safety spec of these things because there's no formal definition of a car
You're just gonna have to use statistical safety
You're not gonna want to code all of this in
You know this this very restricted
C because you're never gonna get any sort of modern performance
You're never gonna get all the niceties OBE how it's gotten in Python, by the way
You're never gonna get you're not gonna be able to be competitive
Tesla autopilot is coded in C++, but it's a very
Nice high-end abstracted C++ not the kind of low end stuff that the car manufacturers are doing so
Tesla is using neural networks. They're using GPUs. We're using neural networks. We're using GPUs
We're using all the same tricks. So we're not actually going to pass autopilot. We're gonna kind of tie him
So we do this right and I hadn't thought that the reason that other cars didn't have autopilot
Was that the car manufacturers did not know how to build it?
This is not true
So I met with the car makers I met with several CEOs
Drove down to their offices. I met with a lot of business development people. I'm still kind of confused about what business development is
Oh, I was I was I was appalled
You couldn't you couldn't talk to these people?
There is no I guess it makes sense when you think about it Ford is a four hundred thousand person organization
Who is Ford if I had mind control over the CEO of Ford?
I still couldn't make this stuff ship
It's like a big it's like a big boat and no one's really skewing. Everyone's got like a little paddle, right?
Question on your right in the back
Yeah, so I think I'm your worst nightmare because I'm both a business development person and a PhD in psychology. You're not gonna take
So if you're appalled now, you should be a little worried. Um my question
Listening to the way you're thinking about going at the problem what you're trying to solve
Makes me think back to your slide with that big red X on it
yeah, and in the way I shorthand of what you did was you put a big red X through the category or the the
Topics having to do with the ethics
and the
Interaction between the technology you're working on in people and I know the baby case could be put off as an edge case
I taught probability I get it
Yeah, but that's a placeholder for a whole bunch of issues that aren't about whether pythons gonna cut it for me or not
And so I'm wondering how you think about that as you develop your technology
I
mean I get look I
Understand big companies and challenges moving through but I think there's a pretty fundamental one when we're looking at some of this stuff around
Assisted driving autonomous driving, whatever part of it you think you want to address?
So when it comes to what I put an extra was people talking specifically about the the ethics of autonomous vehicles
The handoff problem is absolutely real on the problem of making sure
Of just remove from a from like an HCI perspective
Understanding whether the human is in control of the car whether the machine is in control of the car making sure expectations are correct
Oh, these things are extremely important. I
Don't go into it in this slide deck, but we have some medium posts about we have a camera facing the driver
I mean we make sure that the driver is paying attention at all times that we expect them to be paying attention
We make sure our our transition system
When we how we alert how we do the handoffs has been praised by a bunch of people
Auto makers it like beeps and flashes like a little icon. You have no idea what it means
We have consistent messaging about whether the car is capable of doing this whether it's capable of engaging here
So I think things like that are extremely important
What I don't think is important is the kind of people who give far reaching twenty years from now
We're going to rethink cities around autonomous vehicles
Are we what's the difference to the autonomous vehicle and a non autonomous vehicle at most its cost?
In these cases. It's also building a product that is more convenient for a user but from an external perspective
The car looks identical you can't tell
If you see a test on the highway with their cars on autopilot or not on autopilot, I'm sorry
I don't mean to group those two things together. I think one is extremely important I think one is
People self-promoting and stuff that like, I don't see the relevant stuff, but does that answer cool?
So, yeah, you you try to work with these uh with these automakers and
You can't
It's a structural problem
Mobileye has more business development people than they do R&D engineers. That's why their text not that great, but it's in all the cars
So, yeah, I mean to go back to the Paul Graham tweet
You don't realize it. The car manufacturers don't realize
when you get in some of these cars and you use the their adaptive cruise control the
Quality varies wildly from manufacturer to manufacturer. It's almost like these people have never gotten in a Tesla and tried it
So yeah, what do you do? So is this hard as hard at the beginning of the company this was like my plan
I'm gonna sell to these people. I'm gonna talk with them. They're gonna be reasonable
So I realized that who really cares if Tesla is the iPhone
We just have to build the Android and the phones already exist
It's not like we have to get
manufacturer by n we just have to get
Manufacturer compatibility, I would much rather work with the product than the company
Open pilot already supports this whole list of cars
you can go right now and
you can put open pilot in these cars and it will take over the steering the gas and the brakes and it will do a
Significantly better job than the manufacturer system in all of those cars
open pilot is the Android and
Just like Android
It's open source
Why make it open source well
Nobody has any excuse anymore
You've seen it in the last two years how many companies try to raise money off of a demo video of self-driving?
nobody
Because if you can't build something better than what's available and open source and market of it nobody knows that Stanford codes open source
You have nothing right? There is no reason for somebody now to start from scratch on this stuff
Just take open pilot modify. It build it extend it and hopefully
upstream your stuff change the conversation from
Intellectual property and business development deals and exclusivity to do a pull request on an open pilot
Well, upstream it. It's it's everybody's MIT license
So somebody else could take this rebrand it call it their own great. I just want to see the stuff you better
Have you tested
Open pilot and all of those
vehicles that you had previously you have um
So not not personally but so we have a we have we have a safety model
I can go into after after I run through the slide deck
I can go through I can go to the website and show what our safety model is
so our safety model involves
It's two things
It's one
Make sure that the system can never do anything
quickly
make sure it can never like jerk the wheel or slam on the brakes or do something faster than a driver could react and to
Make sure the driver is paying attention at all times
And as soon as they touch either the gas or the brake the car immediately reverts to manual mode
So as long as you ensure those two things you have a pretty good level to safety model
Um and yet be explicit about this. So we say like it cannot do anything bad within one second
So as long as you're paying attention, you know just reach out and it's not like it'll ever like turn the wheel like this
It's really designed for highway driving kind of stuff
So if you just reach out put a little bit of pressure on the steering wheel, it'll just stop doing anything
So yeah, yeah making sure this stuff is well done
and also the safety code is not a Python on the safety code isn't see the safety code is is on an as will be
microcontroller
The stuff that's in Python is like the machine learning model part of things
Which you're never going to be able to formally validate. Anyway, the safety code is formally validated
It has tests it is you got to do it stuff correctly
I am Ashley McCorkle from Intel and
Just let you know we haven't killed mobile yet. We're trying really hard not to that was kind of an expensive acquisition but and
You actually have a lot in common in your approach and am nons approach with mobile
I and one is trying to scale up from ADAS into more sophisticated
Levels of autonomous driving, I think. The other is assuming that this will never work if you have to put you know
multiple xeon
supercomputing resources in a car
You know
he's trying to scale it up from basically like a a
In SOC like a very light computing and addling thousands rather than tens of thousands of dollars the price of a car
Right. So one of his assumptions though, and I think it's relevant for the
Lead up with that we had previously the the warm up on trends in AI is
Rather than trying to use a brute-force approach
Where you were I think you like you were saying, you know
Having 3d lidar mapping of the entire terrain and having these massive crunching to be able to map
You know in 3d, you know everything entire surroundings the car
Using a very light compute method that is really based not on, you know
these deep learning based number crunching but on a rules-based approach and I think he's also published that as you know,
basically open sourcing this responsibility sensitive safety where you're programming a set of
rules into the AI
that that
Basically encapsulate what society's idea of safe driving is and by society
It can be a little bit flexible as well. Like an Israeli car can drive differently than a French car than an American car
So what do you think of that approach and and you do you agree with that particular?
assessment of AI and brute force computation in cars
so
Multi parts here. I've watched I've watched all of his recent talks
Especially especially after auto pilot comes out. I really I'm going to respect
His perspective so a lot more give a very good cvpr talk where he went into
Actually, like what it takes to make these computer vision things reliable enough to drive cars. I
thought the formalization of
that
Stuff he goes into one where he talks about like formally specifying what it means to be a safe driver. I
Think that stuff was pretty weak. The problem is
What he's really trying to do there the subtext is we want to make sure we are never liable for any accidents we caused
I mean you can view the world that way and sell like lawyers and accountants view the world
I don't I want to figure out an engineer. I want to drive accidents down to zero. Let's root cause it let's figure it out
NTSB not nishta
So I also don't think it really works from a technical perspective because take a
double yellow line
The rules of driving say you cannot cross the double yellow line
But if you do not cross double yellow lines and you're driving around San Francisco, you will never get anywhere
There's an uber with their blinkers on right there. Okay, so then when is it?
Okay, do we formalize this or do we look at big data?
My argument is that the definition of driving is what people do when they drive
Now you say not everybody's a safe driver is the anna karenina quote
Every good driver is good in the same way
Every bad driver is bad in a different way because of that the statistical algorithm earning algorithms
Kind of ignore the bad data because they can't find much signal in it
Instead of thinking of the average driver think of a committee driver
Think of 100 people sitting in a room voting 100 times a second on what the car should do
Some of them may be drunk
Some of them may be distracted and some of them may be asleep, but the committee will probably still make the correct decision
So I think that's more the approach and when you try to formalize this stuff even trying to formalize what a car is
becomes extremely hard
So, I don't know. I don't think it's gonna
Gonna go anywhere. I think the way to actually do this is with big data and statistics
Jenna has a question
Yeah, I work for a big insurance company
So I'm curious in your safety stats when you talk about it if you're gonna cover it great
I can't find any data as to when open pilot actually came about so I'm curious how long it's existed and then to
When it's been in an accident
How is fault determined and how is that?
Dealt with so I have some stats on a later slide, but it's a dash cam as well
So we've had no
At fault accidents so far but the system engaged
Which is better than the average you'll see how many miles we have but
How is fault determined
I mean the exact same way it's determined the human is still legally in control car open pilot is a level 2 system
So just like Tesla autopilot or just like imagine you put your car on cruise control, right?
You can't say well, I understand. I rear-ended you but the car was on cruise control and it wasn't supposed to
Great, you're liable. So liability is determined in the exact same way that a
An accident between two humans would be determined right
In fact people think that the problem with these kind of systems is you can't introspect and ask them
You can't say why did you make that decision?
You can't ask humans either if you go after a car accident and ask humans
What happened there recall is extremely bad if you have dashcam footage from both cars
Now you start to figure out what happened
um
So I think devices like this which also function as cloud dash cams will be an extreme boon to the insurance industry
Here you go right away instant fault. I like insurance. I like the whole businesses
Well, the whole business is great its statistics. It's we're going to drive down accident
So we're gonna charge and we're gonna make art we're gonna make our profits
Great
So yeah, how is fault determined in the exact same way that is with humans
So yeah open pilot is not it's not some oh
Hi, so I am a human machine teaming engineer so
You talked earlier about automation as a gradual rise rather than as a cliff
There's a lot of work on levels of automation like you were talking about do you expect to open pilot to eventually
You know climb that gentle slope to full automation? And if so,
What do you expect to need to change or grow and capabilities to achieve that if not, why not?
Yes, I do
The so we're gonna need a few more okay right now it only has one forward-facing camera, that's clearly not enough
You'll need 360 degrees of vision. I think you'll need a bit more compute than what you currently have
If you really want to say the human doesn't have to pay attention
You'll need to talk about like systems reliability engineering. You'll need to put two
Processors and making sure that failure cases are not just right now
A lot of failure cases we have or safety model is based around having a human driver in the driver seat
so as long as we don't kind of have
False positives it's okay, but you start to get into true negative is becoming really bad as well
if you're trying to remove the human from the system, so
Do we eventually get there? Yeah. When are we ready for it when the statistics show we are
when we start to see in the statistics, oh
Wow, open pilot has driven this stretch of road 1 million times and has never made a mistake. Is that good enough?
Figure out those statistics and let's see maybe ask the question. Uh
Yeah, but kind of an add-on question. So you were talking earlier as well about
Restrictions in the utility of full automation in terms of the you know, the larger system that the car is driving in
what are your thoughts about that going forward that just the
Ecosystem of consumer desires will change and legislation will follow or what?
And the design of traffic systems
It'll be gradual it'll be what makes sense
Like I don't know I don't think it's gonna change that much because I don't think machines and humans are that different
I think that the things that
Have been developed over hundreds of years for human drivers will actually work out to be
Oh, well, those things are actually pretty useful for machine drivers, too
Like you're like well machines won't need stop signs. Oh, I forgot about that whole scam v2v communication
Machines won't need stop signs. The two cars will just communicate with each other. This is horrific
This is I don't know if anybody knows anything about safety who comes up with ideas like this because now you need two
Active components to work correctly for a stop sign to work
The beauty of stop signs is a decentralized as the logic
Either party most accident there would be so many more accidents on the road today
If every driver wasn't actively avoiding accidents. Think about every time you hear a horn honk that's an accident
That would have happened if I didn't actively swerve you need both parties to be paying attention
so yeah with respect to like changing these things radically
I don't know. I think that what's good for you most to be good for machines as well
some things are already becoming less relevant like road signs since everybody doesn't have
Like like signs saying oh this exit here. Okay, so yeah open pilot is not
Some fancy research stuff. This was actually my drive to the conference. I guess. I'm on my way to the conference Oh
piles driving right now
It's got the wheel. It's got the gas at the brake
It's got the bridge traffic I have the car in the parking lot. Maybe there's driver I
Know that's in the back. So I noticed there's no rearview mirror
So we don't encourage people to do that
You do not you you you do not have to remove your rear view mirror for driving
but this is still a road-legal car on swivel law in California is you need to have two mirrors on your car that can see
The back if you have to side members, you don't actually need a regular that's more of just an aesthetic taste on my part
But we do not encourage people to do that and the kit does not require it because that would violate FMVSS
But you can do it personally
Doesn't it doesn't violate anything?
So yeah business was simple profit off hardware. I
Mean, you know, it's a business model. I can respect we make the hardware for less than we sell it for
We don't license IP
Ya on the website you buy the three components separately I think it was 600 mm
Don't you need all three you do? Yeah. It's about it's about
$650 for all of them. Yeah. Should we make this easier? Yeah, we should we should make it easier. I don't know
I'm the head of research now. I used to be CEO. I'm not anymore
We'll get a real CEO who who knows things about execution and business right now. We got a new CEO. He's great, but
Uh
Yeah, so it could just about stats. We've driven a point five million miles
So yeah to not have seen to not have seen the system calls accident an eight point five million miles
It's pretty good. We've seen a bunch of accidents with the system engaged
There is one that's particularly hilarious
There's a the system comes to stop behind a car, but the car overshot the stop line
And the driver just puts it reverse and just Rams right into it
Good thing you had the dash cam footage. All right
So first some comparison whammo just reached ten million miles and cruise probably has about 1 million to have significantly more than them
I'm the one that I did not put there is Tesla which has billions of miles on your left in the back again real quick
Over what time span is this? This is oversold. Well, it's been around now for almost three years
Times this is the life timing system
This question will be shorter
When you have a deep learning based approach, yeah and you know, it's really a game of getting a bunch of training datum
so
And what competitive disadvantage does that put a smaller company like yourself? I mean if you back to your Tesla example, right?
Yeah, these are V. Say Wemo or Tesla which are just going to be piling on the
training models
We train our models on only about 100,000 miles of data
Um, the models are not even trained on all the data and we have almost the same number of miles way now
so so to pull out my
amnon
Well, we don't have any small blows, right
But they're not we send all the video back. He would say that, you know if you're trying to
Specifically avoid crash situations that you know that you it's a very low probability event
Yeah, so therefore you would need billions of miles okay in order to properly train
This system against these sorts of events
And also every time you update the system you need another billion
you know billions of miles in order to retrain the model for to avoid these events, so
Is deep learning really the
Scalable approach particularly for a small company. Yes
Um, so the former part of that about needing billions of miles to get to level 4
I completely agree if you 1 billion miles is 10 fatalities, maybe five fatalities
You have to have that kind of stuff in your dataset. If you're trying to say to your systems level 4
Do you need to gather new billion miles? No, you need some good statistical way to
Show that your system can function on replace
Um, so we can just rerun the new system over the billions of miles and say it's still good. Um does deep learning scale? Yes
You have to start to do you're not going to train on all billion miles and you don't have to
When you want to deal with crash scenarios, we're gonna have like a data set where it's like here's 1 million near crash scenario
These are the good ones. This is what you should do. We can do automatic recovery on that stuff, too
So I got two minutes let me just get through the last few slides here this is daily miles driven
And this is daily percent of miles engaged
More than 50 percent of the miles are being driven by the system and this is crushing Tesla Tesla's about 30
Their reason are is is significantly higher is because we don't disengage on the steering wheel and everything is just more
Gradual and gentle we view it as much more of a system than an autopilot
But our goal is to get that number up to 100
So it's kind of growing over time. We got some new users who were less power users
It's also engaged last around the winter because there's snow on the roads
So we expect to see a hump in the middle of every year
Yeah, so how to scale and win
We already have a product people pay for and use daily
continue to improve driving quality and car support
Lower the barrier to entry you don't have to buy three reared animal named things and then partner dealerships for mass distribution
Don't try to talk to don't try to talk to the OEMs. I think it's hopeless
If you partner with dealerships, it's like partnering with you you got your phone and the AT&T store in the t-mobile store
I've talked with some dealerships
They're super hungry for this kind of stuff and they're the kind of people who you can talk to
you're like look we make this thing we sell it to you for $600 you sell it to people for
$2,000 you give $1400
That's a good deal
Since you just did when Twitter, I call me and Instagram George Hotz
Let's talk
When I'm back in your left, please. All right. There was a question over here first, and then we'll come back
Yes, so
How do you deal with and you answered it a little bit or at least hinted at it because of the the winter comment?
All the sensors on these cars are in different places. They have different
limitations or blind spots
How do you deal with the fact that your hundred thousand miles of training data? Probably doesn't
accommodate
Degraded conditions and so how do you build models and understand how they vary and these in these degraded capacities because
Your system. I understand that the sort of the humans always engage, but at the same time
The AI is going to be generating some faulty data and how do you detect that?
Yeah, it's not generating faulty data
And we do have a huge diversity of weather conditions and locations in our data set the data set just comes from all the users
So we have whatever the users are actually driving on
So that's not really that big of a problem
When it comes to the sensors being different
This is why we have the eland the EON has a camera on the back of it that cameras the same across all the cars
The radars are similar enough and the actuators are similar enough that we built a hardware abstraction layer on that
abstracts them to this uniform
API that gives it to all cars and going a lot more into technical details of that but uh
Yeah. So again, it's level 2 if the car like traction control fires. It's like the ESC fires we disengage
We're like you got to be driving right now. Just like you should not use cruise control on the snow
You should not use these systems if there's snow on the road if there's snow on the side of the road. Yes sure, it's fine
Robert
Did you still have a question?
My question was around you mentioned the cloud storage of the dashcam video
Is that a subscription model or how does that work right now? It's free, but we're moving towards
Yeah, we're looking into that kind of stuff
It's expensive storage is expensive
Ok Zee, and then we'll pop back up this
You're tracking all the location data
What is your how do you manage the privacy around that you by using our system you consent to giving us full access to all?
the data
If you don't if you're not ok with that, don't use it. I'm very open about that. I'm not like Facebook
I'm not wishy-washy you are giving us all the data and we will use it for whatever we want if you're not ok with that
Don't use the system
Right side so I have two quick questions one is have you found any issues with
contextualizing how people drive in different regions
I know in Buenos Aires for example as soon as you see a yellow on the other direction
You start going in see see where I'm from. You kind of let rides Lauren out
I always imagine taking half DC drivers and half Buenos Aires drivers and watching what would happen
So when you have these voting's you have differing dimensions. The other one is is
Are you looking at the attention data as people are going more confident in the system?
Are they more willing or more likely to pull out their phone or start losing their attention because they don't have to again here
We're starting to get in a situation where people are feeling pretty safe on this up on the highway
And they're not paying attention anymore
This is why after the second Tesla accident where the guy hit the guardrail we're like we have to ship driver monitoring immediately
So right now if you're driving and you look at your phone if you look at your phone for more than four seconds
it will beep and
Then it will continue to steer but it will stop gasps. It will stop doing the gas
So if you are distracted, it won't accelerate anymore
And then people learn eventually if this becomes a problem, we're also gonna put in lock outs
But that hasn't really become a problem yet. Tesla should do driver monitoring as well
So yeah, as people have become more common
That's the danger as these things get better people pay attention less and that's you just solved with driver monitoring make sure the driver actually
Pays attention and punish them for not
And then the contextualization of regions, oh regionalization. Um, so we just have a country filter right now
Most of the data comes from America it works. The best in America driving is similar enough in America
You will get into weird edge cases, maybe like the Pittsburgh left
I think the way to solve that problem long term is to train different models for different regions
It's like the iPhone has different stuff. He's loading the region model
Okay, maybe time for one more
You have a
Security aspect of it. Sorry. Could you raise your hand wherever you are? Oh right in the middle
Yes security aspect against hacking for Oakland pilot. Um, so
Car hacking is one of these things that also people make a ton of money talking about in conferences
Can you give an example of what it actually happened?
But at least you have seen situations where people have
You know had a gang, you know a regular laptop or something talking to the canvas
Oh, yeah, I've seen I've seen Charlie Miller do a PR stunt
But I've never seen car hacking does not appear to be an actual threat by malicious actors in the real world
When it does I'll consider it much more seriously, but like until it does like what are people really going to do. They're not
It's not really a thing but use industry standard security. Don't do stupid things
Thank you speaking from experience though. If you want to sell your system in certain countries like China, yeah
Oh, we've given up on that mark. Yeah, they have a lot of restrictions and
They actually want to be able to monitor the AI
because they're very
Paranoid about about cyber security our stuff gets into China through github. I'm not I'm not touching that market
I'm not working with no people like that
Okay, well I personally think this was a great way to stop the conference cuz this is one of those
This is a talk where I'm like one minute
I'm like, yeah
I'm really on board with that and then the next no I hate what you just said and then the next minute
I'm like, yeah, I really and then I'm back to
But talk about a provoking way to stop the conference George. Thanks very much